A Guide to the Papers of John Carr Rogers ca. 1910-1978, 1993
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Carr Rogers ca. 1910-1978, 1993
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6803-aq
This collection consists of the papers of artist John Carr Rogers (1907-1979) of Alexandria, Virginia, ca. 1910-1978, 1993, and undated, ca. 1,500 items (7 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These materials from the estate of John Carr Rogers were purchased by the University of Virginia Library from Daniel G. Joyce, Blacksburg, Virginia, on August 30, 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Rogers contributed to small magazines like The Rebel Poet and The Anvil in the thirties, was an artist with the Civilian Conservation Corps in 1935 until he transferred to the Federal Writer's Project, and served in the army during World War II, as Staff Sergeant, 1050th Army Air Forces Base Unit (1942-1945). After the war, he attended the Corcoran School of Art, Washington, D.C., full-time under the G.I. Bill. Rogers passed the Civil Service examination for Illustrator and began working as a government artist. At one point he was suspended from government work for "subversive activity" but later won reinstatement and back pay through the courts. His drawings became a standard feature of the Travel Section of The Washington Daily News, which later also contained Rogers' own illustrated articles. Many of these travel drawings are present in the collection.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of artist John Carr Rogers (1907-1979) of Alexandria, Virginia, ca. 1910-1978, 1993, and undated, ca. 1,500 items (7 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3 linear feet), including correspondence, legal papers, photographs, photograph albums, negatives, and slides, including some artwork by Rogers. Rogers' artwork includes watercolors, pen and ink drawings, pastels, cartoons, illustrations, lead cuts (one mounted on a wood block), linoleum cuts (most mounted on wood blocks), two woodcuts, and sketchbooks.
Also present is a folder of correspondence with various government employees and officials concerning his suspension from government work. Correspondents include Senator Harry F. Byrd and Senator Guy M. Gillette, Rogers's lawyer, Byron N. Scott, and Secretary of the Treasury, George Humphrey.
Arrangement
Alphabetical order by category.
Contents List
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers 1938-1970, n.d., 11 folders (Box 1)
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers n.d., 4 folders (Box 2)
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers - Lead Cuts and a copper engraved nameplate n.d. (Box 2)
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers - Prints and Cards n.d. (Box 2)
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers - Scrapbook of Examples 1939-1963, n.d. (Box 2)
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers - Print Blocks n.d. (Box 2)
  including a man reading, farm scene and bar scene (not mounted on a wood block)
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers - Lead Cut Portrait of a Woman, mounted on a wood block n.d. (Box 3)
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers - Lino Cuts of Christmas Greetings from the Rogers Family 1951-1976, n.d., 6 lino cuts, all mounted on a wood block (Box 3)
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers - Lino Cuts [ca. 1930s], 1945, n.d. (Box 3)
  including men playing checkers on an army bunk, "The Broken Hand," "Lime Kiln at Strasburg, Virginia," factory scene, and a house possibly belonging to Rogers (5 lino cuts, all mounted on a wood block)
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers - Wood Cuts of a Tree and Rural scene n.d., 2 wood cuts (Box 3)
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers - Sketchbooks ca. 1942-1977, n.d., 6 folders (Box 4)
- Artwork by John Carr Rogers and articles by or about Rogers from The Foolkiller 1947-1978, n.d. (Oversize OS)
- Certificate - Honorable Discharge from the Army 1945 (Box 5)
- Correspondence 1946-1975, 1993, n.d. (Box 5)
- Correspondence re the suspension of John C. Rogers from government work 1955-1958 (Box 5)
- Legal Papers - Civil Actions 1956, 1959 (Box 5)
- Negatives 1980, n.d. (Box 5)
- News clippings re John C. Rogers and his work 1952-1978, n.d. (Box 5)
- Photographs - John Carr Rogers ca. 1935-1975, n.d. (Box 5)
- Photographs - Family 1913, n.d. (Box 2 folders)
- Photographs - Friends, mostly identified ca. 1936-1949 (Box 5)
- Photographs - Middleton Mill, Middleton, Virginia, and "Ben Venne," near Sperryville, Virginia ca. 1910, n.d. (Box 5)
- Photographs - Miscellaneous ca. 1942-1975, n.d. (Box 5)
- Photograph Album of John C. Rogers ca. 1923-1924, n.d. (Box 5)
- Photograph Album of John C. Rogers 1911-1922, n.d. (Box 6)
- Photograph Album of John C. Rogers 1928-1931, n.d. (Box 6)
- Photograph Album of John C. Rogers n.d. (Box 6)
- Photograph Album of Minnie E. Rogers 1913 and n.d. (Box 6)
- Photograph Album of John C. Rogers, with many loose photographs from the album foldered separately (fragile condition) 1921-1947, n.d. (Box 7)
- Poetry n.d. (Box 7)
- Slides, some concerning the work of John C. Rogers ca. 1967-1973, n.d. (Box 7)
- Slides ca. 1974-1975, n.d. (Box 7)